Now, from the left coast, it's another podcast edition of the Peter B. Collins show.
Peter B. is curious, opinionated, and relentless in pursuit of the truth like a honey bee drawn
to pollen.
He's an independent progressive, ready to sting Republicans and Democrats alike when
they deserve it.
For years in commercial radio, Peter B. welcomes you to this audio adventure in news and politics
with no corporate filter.
Listeners support this program and you can help at PeterB.Collins.com.
Here's your humble host, Peter B.
Thanks for grabbing the latest in-depth interview podcast from PeterB.Collins.com.
Today I'm pleased to present a conversation with John Kiriakou.
He's the only CIA officer who went to jail related to our torture program and he didn't
torture anybody.
He's got a powerful new book out called Doing Time Like a Spy, How the CIA Taught Me to Survive
and Thrive in Prison.
And he's got some fascinating stories about who controls the TV set, the ritualized segregation,
and the low-lifes in uniform called correctional officers.
It's quite a conversation and it's coming your way in seconds.
This podcast is made possible by listeners who support me with your subscriptions.
People like Benny Alto, William Genetta, Terry Parris, and Carla Mahoney.
I'm grateful for their support and I'd like to have yours.
You want to arrange it?
Come on over to PeterB.Collins.com.
You click on menu, pull it down, click on Become a Subscriber.
That takes you to the sign-up page where you can choose a subscription that fits
your budget.
Thanks for your support.
Today on the PeterB.Collins podcast, John Kiriakou returns to the program to talk about
his life behind bars.
His new book is called Doing Time Like a Spy, subtitled How the CIA Taught Me to Survive
and Thrive in Prison.
And in the early pages of the book, Kiriakou admits that he adopted an asshole persona
while he was in the federal pen.
One of my favorite spook tunes from Was Not Was, Spy and the House of Love, and I don't
think that the federal prison in Loretto, in Pennsylvania, is quite a house of love.
But John Kiriakou spent a little under three years there, and he's written a powerful new
book about it that has some surprises in it.
John, welcome back to the PeterB.Collins podcast.
Thanks very much.
Very happy to be here.
Well, it's nice to talk to you again, and before we dive into the book, tell our
listeners a little bit about your recent travels.
You just did a trip to Europe where you spoke to many important audiences, and your message
appears to have a little more traction outside the United States than it does inside.
You know, it really does.
This has been revelatory for me.
I went last week to Iceland, Germany, Luxembourg, Belgium, and Ireland.
You sound like an American blues musician on tour where the money is.
It was mostly to talk about national security whistleblowing and transparency.
There were four separate events in Germany.
I sat on panels at two film festivals in Luxembourg and Belgium, and the crazy thing
is that these were not gatherings of fringe people or WikiLeaks people.
I was on panels with the Luxembourg Minister of Justice, the German Minister of Foreign Affairs.
I spoke to the German Parliament on my third day there, and then had lunch with the National
Security Advisor.
I was taken aback that people in such important positions, people with such prominent roles
in national security, really wanted to know what I had to say about transparency
and about the classification of criminal acts.
So, man, it was nothing like the treatment I've gotten in the United States over the
last five and a half years.
And John, nominally, our Bill of Rights gives Americans significant additional freedoms.
For example, I did some media consulting work in Berlin a few years ago, and we
learned about the German laws that do not provide the kind of robust freedom of speech
that we still nominally enjoy in the United States.
And there was also just a tremendous cultural resistance to expressing personal opinion
in public.
And I was training these Germans on how to do American-style talk radio, and I had
to feed them sentences.
I believe that Chancellor Cole is, and I'd say finish that sentence, and they would
say, the Chancellor.
Oh, yeah, and in the U.K., it's far, far worse than it is even in the United
States because not only do they have this awful law called the Official Secrets Act,
which essentially bars anybody from saying anything having to do with national
security, but they actually use that law as an iron fist to crack down on whistleblowers
and potential whistleblowers.
So what was your takeaway from their interest in your talk about transparency
in the era of the expanding national security and surveillance state?
Well, I think my takeaway is that they were reluctant to do anything to upset the
United States while Barack Obama was president, just because Obama had
engaged them on issues, and while they disagreed with the American position
on whistleblowing and transparency, they were willing to keep quiet about it,
but they're perfectly panic-stricken over President Trump, and now they're willing
to put their foot down.
That's interesting.
And take a moment, because you put up a Facebook post that really jazzed me,
and I'm not sure why you didn't include the episode of Ai Wei Wei, his
arch-show at Alcatraz, and the, what, 1,500 postcards that you
received from people who experienced that art exhibit, but let me explain
that I went to Alcatraz that was 2.5, 3 years ago, and Ai Wei Wei created
this exhibit at the prison, which was about political prisoners, and in one
of these huge warehouse spaces, he laid out a huge tableau.
It was a tapestry made of Legos, and on the Legos were cast his line
of drawings of over 100 political prisoners who were at that point
incarcerated worldwide, and after you viewed the exhibit, you went to another
room where you were invited to sign a postcard, and he created a custom
postcard for each political prisoner, and I sent one to you, and one
to Chakar Amar at Guantanamo, and I thought it was just a powerful
process that engaged the people who attended this, many of whom were just
on the typical tour of Alcatraz, and you had a surprise encounter with Ai Wei Wei.
It's the craziest thing. I was, I'm on the board of the Courage Foundation,
which is a Berlin-based whistleblower protection group, and so we had
our first ever board meeting, and it was in a part of Berlin that I had
never been to before, and I had to rush from the meeting to the airport,
so I had my luggage with me, and I'm in this strange, odd part of town
pulling my suitcase, and there's this Chinese man walking toward me,
and he says, John Kiriaku, and I look at him, and he says,
very softly, I am Ai Wei Wei, and I said, oh my gosh, what a small world.
And I, we had been in touch previously by Skype, but he was
under house arrest in China, and so we stood there on the street.
I thanked him profusely for doing my portrait out of Legos at the show
at Alcatraz, and he invited me back to his studio, so I left the
meeting an hour early, dragged my suitcase over to his studio,
which was about another mile away.
He was just out for a random stroll.
Wow.
We bumped into each other, and so he gave me a tour of the studio,
and he autographed, he made these iPhone cases with each of the
portraits on them, and so he gave me an iPhone case with my Lego
portrait on it, and autographed it, and then one of the catalogs
from the show, it was an incredible experience, and I was so
honored and humbled to finally meet him.
Yeah, well, you can't see me, we're just talking by phone
right now, but I am wearing my Ai Wei Wei cap from the
Alcatraz experience, and it made a hell of an impression on
me, I have to say.
On my very first day of house arrest, that was the day that
the show closed at Alcatraz, and the gallery, the San
Francisco-based gallery that assisted him in putting the
show on, knew that I was home that day, and so they
scraped me.
and they walked around the entire show with an iPad so I could see each one of
the portraits. I got to see my own and then in the in the small cells the the
solitary confinement cells he had filled each sink with some with ceramic
doves and ceramic flowers and they showed me all of those as well. It was
it was really incredible and very very generous. Yeah in the cells there were
also depictions that included audio tracks of various prison settings around
the world in many different languages and it was it was really powerful. And and
John I'm a little unusual because I've been active in prison reform my secret
studio it's not so secret but I'm located less than a mile from San Quentin
prison here in California and I have visited there over 120 times. I like to
tell people I've never been invited to spend the night but I I do have quite a
bit of experience and I have to say that your book educated me. I learned
things about what you went through in the federal medium security lockup in
Pennsylvania and I want to start with just the premise of your book. What did the
CIA teach you besides never give any information up even if they torture you
but but how did they educate you and and what skills did you bring to the
prison setting that enabled you to survive avoid getting into fights and
prevail in many of the little petty squabbles that you got involved with.
You know I never even really thought about it until I had been there five days
and there's a little bit of background here. When I was sentenced in in January
of 2012 my attorneys asked my sentencing judge to send me to the minimum
security work camp at Loretto Pennsylvania and minimum security work
camps have no bars on the windows there's no concertina wire the
doors are not locked you're free to come and go as you please you're just sort of
on your honor not to abscond and a lot of the guys work in town there's a
university in town so a lot of them are janitors there and I thought well okay
this is gonna be awful and depressing and I'm gonna be without my family but
at least you know I can be out and about and get on with my life so when
I first arrived at prison I turned myself in and when you do that you
literally just knock on the door and say hi I'm John Kiriakou I'm here to turn
myself in so I did that they frisked me then they put me through a metal
detector and then the corrections officer the CO starts to lead me around
to the back of the actual prison that's across the street from the camp
and I said no no I think there's a mistake I'm supposed to be at the
camp across the street and the the CO chuckles and says not according to my
paperwork you're not and I thought all right take it easy there's nothing you
can do if you make any kind of scene you'll go straight to solitary so just
wait until you can get a phone well it took me five days before I got access to
a phone and then I finally called my attorney and I said hey listen they
put me in the actual prison with the murderers and the pedophiles and the
drug kingpins what do I do and he said well we can file a motion but it
will be two years before we get a hearing and you'll be home by then so I'm
sorry buddy you're gonna have to just tough it out and so it was that day
day five in prison that I decided you're trained for this you've lived in
worst places with more dangerous people you're gonna have to fall back on
your training and so that's what I did now after a while it became kind of
fun or even if not fun just kind of a challenge to help me pass the time and
so I was visiting in the visitor's room one day with a friend of mine who's a
university professor and I was telling him some of these stories and he said you
know I know that that by its nature this whole thing is very depressing but
these stories are really fun and there are some lessons to be learned here
you should write a book about this and so I I did and the book that I ended up
with doing time like a spy I hand wrote on 550 legal pages there are no computers
in prison there are no typewriters and so I just sat down with a legal pad and
started writing and early in the book as I mentioned in the introduction you
said you know if you met me there you'd think I'm pretty much of an asshole oh
yeah and I was you do have to put up a fairly aggressive defensive exterior yes
in order to prevent all kinds of predations you know major or minor I
say later on in the book that prison is a combination of seventh grade Lord of
the flies and a mental institution and that's really what it is if you show
even an inkling of weakness these predators will be on you and you'll
never be able to regain respect you will always be in danger and it's gonna
make the time that much longer I saw this happen while I was there and the
only way out is to check yourself into solitary confinement for your own
protection and I thought well if I have anything to do with it it's people who
are going to be checking themselves into solitary confinement to protect
themselves from me and that's how I went about it you're right this is on
page 67 the sad truth is that most co's correctional officers are assholes
they're power mad bullies passive-aggressive instigators and just
all-around dicks I believe this is for several reasons and you talk about
how they're often rural white guys who can't find a job you don't say this but
in my experience many of them are wannabe cops who didn't you know couldn't
pass either the physical or the written test yeah and so they wind up being a
correctional officer and at least here in California it pays pretty well
there's a lot of overtime they've got a hefty pension system and so it's a
fairly attractive job for somebody with almost no marketable skills there was one
CEO who pulled me aside one day and I actually I'm not going to say that I
liked him I'm gonna say that I didn't dislike him I respected him he was a
nice kid he was probably 20 or 25 years younger than I am and he kind of
whispered hey Kiryaku how do I get into the CIA and I said you know you
seem like a nice guy you're obviously bright what in the world are you doing
here you don't belong here you should apply to the CIA even if it's in you know
the uniformed security division you should at least give it a try and he
thought about it for a minute and he said no I couldn't do that he said my
mom and dad were both CEOs my grandfather was a CEO and my wife would
never want to leave Loretto and this was a town of 1200 people in the
mountains of central Pennsylvania and I thought you know that's the sad thing
because this guy actually had something going for himself but that attitude was
very typical it was very parochial and very local and and you're right I
actually do say in one of the letters from Loretto that I include in this
book that um that the average CEO is is a guy who just couldn't cut it in the
local police academy and who couldn't cut it in the in the military either
yeah yeah it is amazing now another thing that you depict I think quite
accurately and somewhat colorfully is the enforced segregation that occurs in
prison and this is done with the ascent of the management and it it really
comes into focus when you talk about who controls what you're watching in the
TV room right Peter this was again a revelation to me this was 1950s
segregated America and you know each housing unit has a TV room and each TV
room has a handful of TVs I lived in a large housing unit we had six TVs and
three were controlled by the hit by the Hispanics and two by the African
Americans and that's the way it was in every unit people kind of vaguely
mentioned that there had been a riot in the 1990s in and in this riot the whites
lost and they lost their their ownership of the TVs but it gets
ridiculous to the point of comedy um for example every single morning at 6
a.m. one of the Hispanic TVs had law and order on it and nobody ever watched
law and order so I picked one of the Hispanics well he was actually the
Hispanic shot caller the boss of all the Hispanics I said hey Zeus why do you
guys have law and order on this TV every day why don't we put CNN at least we
can see what the heck's going on in the world and he said no that's Domingo's
TV I said well who the heck is Domingo oh he left a couple years ago and I
said well if he's not here anymore then it's kind of not his TV you're
the shot caller you control the TV he said Domingo paid $400
that TV, which is another thing that people do is they'll pay their, their
shotcaller, their, the, the head of their racial group, um, X amount of money.
If you want to chair in the TV room, it's 14 bucks.
If you want to TV, apparently it's 400.
He said, no, Domingo paid 400 for that TV.
That's his TV and he watched law and order every day.
I said, okay.
Well, what a legacy.
Now, now John, that points up that you were a short termer there and you
dealt with many people who had, uh, lengthy sentences, uh, and of course I'm
not clear, uh, if you had lifers there, I would think they would be in maximum
security facilities, but you, you, you can, unless, unless they're pedophiles
because it's too dangerous for pedophiles to be in medium or maximum
security.
So yeah, we, we had some pedophiles who for all intents and purposes had
life sentences.
There was a, there was one particularly awful, horrible man, um, with
whom I worked in the chapel and, um, he was in on his third pedophilia
offense.
So the first offense is a mandatory five year minimum.
So he got out and six months later, he, uh, comes back in for 12 years
and that's where I met him.
So he was in his late sixties when I met him and at the very end of
his sentence of his 12 year sentence.
So he's out and then three months later, here he is in the chapel again.
I said, cook, what are you doing here?
Well, he says, I have a problem.
I said, how much time to give you?
And he said 60 years and I said, you know what, I said, society is
better off with you in here.
Well, and, and you know, John, that's, that's an interesting statement
because when I have visited San Quentin, it is typically to advocate for
someone that I would like to see released from prison, but each time
I go in the visiting room, uh, the, the impression and the, you know,
feeling that I leave with is, well, you know, we do need prisons and we
do need to separate some people from, uh, society.
You're right, Peter.
Uh, you know, I've come to the conclusion that we don't need minimum
security work camps.
If your crime is so minor that they're going to put you in a
place where you're free to come and go and free to work in town,
then wear an ankle bracelet, stay at home, maintain a job and support
your family and, and contribute to society.
But you're right.
There are some people who are just so dangerous that they just can't
live among us as normal, uh, contributing or productive members of society.
And so we really do need prisons.
What's a chomo, John?
Chomo is prison slang for a child molester.
I had never heard that word, uh, in my life until the day that I
arrived and I heard it twice in the same day.
Um, I was approached, I had been in prison about two hours and, and I
was approached by two, uh, neo-nazis.
Uh, a CEO had told me when he was checking me in that if, if
somebody walks into your cell uninvited, that's an act of aggression.
And sure enough, after two hours, these two neo-nazis walk right into my
room, one with an enormous swastika that took up the entire front half of his
neck and, um, and he said to me, I jumped up and I put my, I put my
fists up and I said, what do you want?
And I was trying to, you know, be as, as tough and as big as I could
make myself look.
And he says, take it easy.
Are you the new guy?
And I said, yeah, so, and he said, are you, uh, a fag?
And I said, no, are you a rat?
I said, no, I didn't have anybody in my case.
Are you a chomo?
And I said, I never heard that word before.
So he says, chomo child molester.
And I said, no, I'm not a child molester.
And he said, okay, then you can sit with the Arians in the cafeteria.
And like I say in the book, I kind of stood there and looked at him and
thought, well, I guess I'm with the Arians now.
Later that day, I met, uh, Frank Russo, uh, Frank became one of my
closest friends and, uh, and my, my bunkmate, he had been the, uh,
mayor of Cleveland, Ohio.
And then he was the auditor general of Cuyahoga County, Ohio, and was
actually arrested on corruption charges.
While he was running for governor of Ohio, Frank was just a wonderful,
kind and sweet guy.
Well, he had never heard the word chomo either.
So somebody walked up to him and said, Hey, are you a chomo?
And Frank said, no, I'm Russo.
And the guy said, what?
You crack and wise with me.
And he said, no, I'm not chomo.
Maybe chomo's coming on the bus next week.
And he said, the war, he protested that his name wasn't chomo.
The angrier this Arian got and Frank, he is 67 years old.
He thought, Oh no, I'm going to get my ass kicked here.
Finally, the guy was just so perplexed.
He walked away and I laughed.
I said, Frank, I never heard the word either.
It had to be explained to me.
Now, John, let me be candid that one of the things that kind of
shocked me about the narrative in your book is that you are really allergic,
if not highly antagonistic to anyone who is tagged as a pedophile
or a child molester or kitty porn convict.
And I do understand in a prison setting, things are different
and it can represent more than just an annoyance.
But the my takeaway from the book is that you were pretty radicalized
about sex offenders and you cut them absolutely no slack.
Zero, zero slack.
I, you know, I, to the best of my knowledge, I've never met a pedophile.
I, you know, thank God I was never molested as a child.
I don't know anybody who was, at least in my family or among my friends.
At least nobody's ever said anything.
So I never had an exposure to somebody like this.
And my very first, I had been at Loretto study four days
and I started working in the prison library before I got my chapel job.
And my job was to wipe off the tables.
And so the leader, I guess, or the head of the cleaning crew
said to me, Hey, are you the new guy?
And I said, Yeah, well, welcome to the library.
I said, Yeah, thank you.
He said, How long you in for?
I said, 30 months.
And he said, Oh, short timer.
That's easy.
I said, Yeah, it feels like 30 years.
How long are you in for?
Oh, I have 24 years, he says.
And I said, 24 years.
Do you mind if I ask you what you did?
And he said, Sure, I got caught looking at crime scene photos.
I said, What the heck is that supposed to mean?
And he said, Well, having sex with children is a crime.
I got caught looking at the photos.
And I said, Oh, come on, you're not a victim here.
And he says, Well, what really did me in was that subfolder?
So I said, OK, I'll bite.
What was in the subfolder?
And he got very excited and animated.
And he said, Well, I like to masturbate while looking at pictures of dead children.
And I have a friend who works at the morgue and I put my hands up.
And I said, Stop, don't ever speak to me again.
You understand?
And he says, Yeah, I understand.
But it wasn't just that it was fully, fully 25 to 30 percent of the prison
and not just Loretto, but any federal prison at the low level is made up of child molesters.
And they congregate, they eat together, they room together,
they exercise together and walk the track and they even have their own
chomo shot collar.
I wasn't sure how to deal with them.
So I wrote a letter to a professor friend of mine.
I had been an adjunct at a university in Washington.
I wrote him a letter and I laid all this out.
And I said, What do I do?
How do I deal with these people?
So he went to the director of the or the chairman of the psychology department
and the chairman wrote me a letter back and said that pedophiles can't be cured.
There's no therapy, there's no medication, there's nothing that can change them.
And the reason why they hang out together and talk about their crimes constantly
is because it gives them sexual gratification to relive those crimes.
So there's no rehabilitation for these guys.
They actually enjoy themselves in prison.
And they were lucky at Loretto.
I heard horror stories about other prisons where people would buy olive oil
in the commissary and then microwave the olive oil until it was boiling.
And then pour it on child molesters while they were sleeping.
Child molesters aren't allowed to have visitors in their cells.
They're not allowed to have seats in the TV room.
They have to sit at designated chomo tables in the cafeteria.
So it was a real learning experience for me.
In the chapel, just as a rule of thumb,
the library and the chapel are real safe zones for child molesters in prison
because there are always COs there.
And they know they're not going to get beaten up there.
So they hang out literally all day from morning until night
in the chapel and the library.
And we had a rule in the chapel that you can't talk about your case.
Right? The chapel is a place of meditation and reflection and prayer.
Nobody wants to hear about your sick case.
But that's all they would do was talk about their cases.
About, you know, there was one, he was a fireman from Haiti.
here's town maryland we called him chomo the giant he was six feet
seven or six eight
and he was going on and on and on about
having sex with a fifteen-year-old daughter and how she came on to him
and she said she liked it and it felt good
and he was videotaping it and he was selling the dvds on online and
everybody just loved them she was so beautiful and i went out there i
said hey
no talking about your case
and he looks at me indignantly
and says
jesus loved the little children
and i i was so flabbergasted by that i just went back into the office and just
sat back down again like you can't even reason with these people
so john are there any other ways that uh... prison changed you changed your
perceptions changed your attitudes toward groups of people or types of
people
yet very very much so
peter before i got in trouble i didn't give five seconds of thought
to the justice system
or certainly to the prison system
not five seconds of thought
and then living through it made me realize what a broken system we have you know
i i threw out the statistic all the time
uh... because it's true and it's shocking and that is
but the united states has five percent of the world's population and twenty
five percent of the world's prison population
we have more
people incarcerated per capita
than the russian
the chinese
even the iranians
that to me is a problem
when when there's no rehabilitation
and no education that's a problem
when mental
uh... health is is treated as a disciplinary problem
that's a problem
when when one out of every four black men in america is either in prison or
jail
or on probation or parole that's a problem
we don't see it as a problem
we we have an attorney general now who wants to reimpose mandatory minimum
sentences on uh... for drug crimes
got up to this point
so that was something that that
really open my eyes and i think he was
you know you you really get to see what happens
in a community
where everybody's poor
where people don't have an educational background or foundation in in
even basic education
where they don't have job skills
they end up in prison
and uh... i don't have a conversation one time
that was just it it was just so stunning to me i don't think i'll ever forget it
there were these
uh... three african-american guys playing cards in the tv room
with middle of the day
all the tv's were on most people were at work or outside to the place is
empty these guys were playing cards
and one of them just kind of looked around and said you know
we get three square meals a day
we get a warm bed
we get clothes
we got tv
we can play cards
we get medical care
if we had pussy
this place would be paradise
john talk a little bit about the price that you have paid but it's always
uh... as i explained when i go to san quentin
i stand in line with family members of prisoners
and they pay an incredible price to stay in connection with their loved one
uh... many people who visit san quentin drove all night from southern
california
uh... often only to be rejected because uh... the person they want to visit
has been locked down or is at work uh... unexpectedly
and so the heartbreak for families is significant
uh... tell us if if your family visited you much while you were in prison
and how they have healed
since you can't uh... have come home
might my family visited me regularly thank god uh... my my wife uh... would
leave the house at four forty five a m uh... uh... they would come once a
month because you're limited as to the number of visits you're allowed to
have
they would come every single month
leave it for forty five a m arrive at eight fifteen the doors open to date twenty
sometimes they couldn't get in until ten o'clock for one reason or another or
for no reason at all
and then they would stay until two fifteen which is when the the cops
throw everybody out
and uh... and then they would start the long track home again
now i was i was fortunate because i really did have a support structure work
most prisoners don't get any visits at all
or visits only very rarely
and many state systems
are converting to something called video visitation
there's uh... there's a company
called uh... jpey
that run these
skype like uh... video terminals
uh... which sounds like a great idea you can put these video terminals in
different cities
and instead of making this long drive like you say a lot of people drive all
night
which is actually quite common
uh... you can just go to a video center but the thing is that they
charge you a dollar a minute
the dollar a minute
to have a visit
who does this affect the most it affects poor people the most
and that's that
the company's point it's to prey on the poor
so when our government says that
that one of their primary objective
in the in the uh...
uh... prison system
is to
reacquaint prisoners with their families to try to help them to reintegrate
with their families and to be good fathers
that's just nonsense
they don't mean that at all
you know why
these visits are a dollar a minute
the bureau of prisons
and the state department of corrections
get a fifty percent kickback
that's why they could they cost a dollar a minute
anything with phone
you know that you you're allowed to have in the federal system three hundred
minutes a month
uh... to call home
so some guys call
and minutes a day
i called fifteen minutes every other day which gave me a little bit of
extra time
uh... every month if something came up and i needed to make a an extra call
but you know twenty six cents a minute
uh... it it adds up
very expensive
and again
we've got the poorest people in society that are incarcerated they can afford to
pay twenty six cents a minute
yeah it's really extortion from the uh... people who are least able to uh...
pay for it
and it's it's a gruesome situation when you see the kickbacks
that are are used to pay to lock up more people
that's exactly right
so uh... your wife heather lost her job at the c i a
uh... just as as you were about to go to trial
yeah it's actually what it was even before that uh... she was fired on the
day of my arrest only because she was married to me
i had been arraigned
and i was in my attorney's car
uh... on the way home he was going to drop me off at home
after the arraignment and uh... she called on my cell phone and she said
well i have bad news
i got fired today and i said what
what happened
and she said they called me in
and she was a maternity leave at the time i should add
so she said they called her in
and they told her
that she could resign
or they were going to put her through
the most hellacious background investigation she could imagine
and she said
that's okay
i don't want to work for an organization
that is treated by husband the way you have treated him
so she submitted her resignation
right there on the spot
and the funny thing is
she was immediately gobbled up by a fortune one hundred company
she's been promoted
three times since then and she makes about triple what she was making at the
cia
but they're lost
and now uh... former cia colleagues are reaching out to her on linkedin
asking if she can get them into this company
that's very interesting
let me ask you a somewhat personal and probing question john
and it's a long one
uh... you were uh... an officer at the cia for fourteen years uh... a fairly
accomplished spy
and uh... you were briefed into the many of the black programs uh... of the
covert operations of the intelligence community
and that made you uh... what i would call a made man
uh... in the the world of covert operations
you were then put through the ringer
uh... by that that same machinery
uh... spent thirty months in prison uh... you are still on parole
and uh... you know in your writings as both before during and since prison
uh... you have struck a a series of positions that make you very popular
with lefties like me
right but but the lingering question is
uh... who are you
well and and the the republican party
and the conservative movement in this country do not have a monopoly on
patriotism
uh... as far as i'm concerned it is
it is we progress
who are the patriots
we're the ones
that want to implement
the plans in the programs that are founding fathers had first conceived
so that you know i i would counter anybody that challenged my politics
by saying that
we're the patriot
uh... i feel very strongly about that
i come from an immigrant family all four of my grandparents came from greece
uh... my my dad's father left
when um... when his uh...
ancestral island was occupied
by the ottoman empire and then
uh... the italians took it after the fall of the ottoman so uh...
they they fled you know they were economic refugees basically is is what
it came down to
and here my grandfather tell the story
franklin roosevelt was you know personally waiting for everybody at
ellis island to give them passports and citizenship and jobs in the steel
mill in pit
And so, all my life, and all my dad's life, my grandfather talked about public service,
that we owed this country so much for what it did for us that we had to pay it back.
My grandfather kept a framed photo of Franklin Roosevelt on the TV until he died in 1978.
I still have that picture of Franklin Roosevelt.
I have it in my bedroom.
So public service was very, very important.
And you know, I wanted to see the world while serving the country.
I had a fascination with the Middle East.
I still do all my life.
And I had an advisor in grad school who was actually a CIA officer undercover as a grad
school advisor.
And he recruited me into the CIA in 1989.
So do you have a clear sense though of who you are after all that you've been through?
And are you still at heart a spy who would like to return to that work and you know, deliver
on missions for our country?
Or do you feel that the agency that you spent 14 years in is tainted and has been assigned
impossible missions and improbable missions as well?
Well, yeah, the CIA is tainted.
And I wouldn't and couldn't go back to the CIA because that's not the CIA that I knew.
In fact, when I was at the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, I worked with a guy who
had been a senior CIA officer.
And we became good friends.
And he said to me one time, you know, you always talk about how much you love the
CIA but how the CIA has changed over the years.
And certainly now it's more of a paramilitary organization than anything else.
And he says, I always chuckle when I hear you say that because the CIA that you describe
never really existed.
It only existed in your mind.
He said it's always been a troubled organization.
It's always been an organization that's been antithetical to the American way of life.
You had a good time, but you were so junior, he said you didn't see what was really going
on upstairs at the top.
And the more I think about that, the more I realize that he was probably right.
I've always been a progressive, I've always been a civil libertarian at the same time.
And the CIA that we have now that gladly carries out operations against American citizens
even is antithetical to the American way of life.
So John, let's segue now to some current issues.
And I do want to highly recommend your book, Doing Time Like a Spy.
It is now published and I read a pre-publication copy, but it's out there and available and
I encourage people to find it and to read it.
But the agency where you used to work is now embroiled in this whole Trump-Russia
embryo.
And I'm a skeptic.
I don't believe the representations that the Director of National Intelligence offered
in October or in January.
The documents that they published are insulting and infantilized.
We have no public evidence of the alleged Russian responsibility for hacking the DNC.
And so much of what we believe to be true or people have embraced is based on anonymous
information leaked by people who we can't identify.
And so we have spun into this evidence-free era where a leak becomes a fact by repetition
and by multiple reporting, but not by proof or multiple sources.
And so I feel that we've entered this hall of mirrors that makes it very difficult
for the average American to know what to believe or who to believe.
Do you have any confidence in the assertions contained in the assessments from October and
January about Russia's attempt to manipulate the election in favor of Trump?
No.
No, I don't.
And I've been quite vocal about this, too, in columns that I regularly write for ReaderSupportedNews.org.
No.
Anytime the intelligence community or the FBI lays out a story and then says, take my word
for it.
Well, don't take their word for it.
I think that this whole notion of hacking, too, is overblown because no one's ever
actually defined what they mean by hacking.
Did the Russians somehow steal the election from Hillary Clinton?
No.
Hillary Clinton was a terrible candidate.
Hillary Clinton stole the primary election from Bernie Sanders.
So if they're accusing the Russians of having hacked voting machines and changed votes or
somehow having stolen the election for Trump, well, my God, that's a serious charge.
Lay out the evidence and let's take a look at it.
But they haven't laid out any evidence, and you're right.
The evidence that they have provided tells us literally nothing.
And with that said, and I part company with a lot of my friends on the left on this issue,
I support the appointment of a special counsel.
Not because I think that there's anything to these Russian issues, but because I think
crimes have been committed by senior members of the Trump campaign.
Mike Flynn, for example, we know failed to register as an agent for a foreign government
when he was lobbying for Turkey.
That is a crime.
We know that he failed to register as an agent for the Russian government when he was taking
money from the Russians to lobby.
That is a crime.
He did not report the whatever it is, $40,000 or $65,000, I've seen both figures, that
he received as payment from the Russian government.
That's a crime.
He filled out incorrect improper information on his ethics report.
That's also a crime.
So that's what I'd like to get to the bottom of.
Flynn, Manafort, Carter Page, possibly Roger Stone.
I'd like to see what was going on inside that campaign.
Getting back to the issue of hacking and the emails though, Ambassador Craig Murray,
the former British ambassador to Uzbekistan who lost his job because he blew the whistle
on the Uzbek torture program, said to the Guardian newspaper in London that a DNC staffer
printed off the Podesta emails and gave them to Craig.
And Craig personally delivered those emails to WikiLeaks.
He says that there was no Russian hack, that he was the middleman between the DNC staff
and WikiLeaks.
But the mainstream media has ignored that assertion.
Well, and the reporting, it's a little rough on the latest developments in the Seth Rich
murder investigation.
But it's much more credible to believe that an insider released that information than
the Russian hack gave it to WikiLeaks.
And your colleagues in the veteran intelligence professionals for sanity, including Bill
Binney, who I've talked to on many occasions, former technical director at the NSA, they
flatly maintain that if it was a hack, that the NSA could trace those packets and could
determine when they were accessed, where they went, and most likely who did it.
We also know that this bullshit about Fancy Bear and APT-28 and the Cyrillic reference
to the founder of the KGB, anybody can create that kind of a false trail.
And everybody is well aware, at least by now, that it's easy to fake your IP address.
Absolutely.
Hackers do it every day.
Yeah.
It's very easy to do.
And the fact that the FBI has never examined the DNC servers, they relied on CrowdStrike
to submit a report, and they just take that at face value.
All of this, you know, truly undermines the, you know, much-vaunted national security apparatus
that we have.
But I do part company with you a bit on the selection of Mueller as the special counsel.
Mainly...
Well, no, no, I'm not a supporter of Mueller.
It was Mueller who headed the investigation that put me in prison.
It was Mueller who created what they called the John Kiriakou Task Force at the FBI.
So, no, believe me, I'm no fan of Mueller.
But I did think that we needed somebody as a special counsel.
Well, I do think, though, that he can be relied upon to, number one, preserve the reputation
of the FBI.
And whatever you define as the deep state, he is a deep actor in the deep state.
And I do believe that he's well positioned to dispatch Trump.
But at what cost?
The cost will be the public role of the deep state in running our country and picking our
presidents as opposed to the murky covert role that has been exercised in the past.
That's true.
You know, there was an interesting editorial in the Washington Post today.
And I generally hate the Washington Post, just because they...
uh... they're so anti whistleblower and it's not just me at any national
security whistleblower but there was a fascinating editorial today in which they
they laid out how trump can save himself and it was by adopting the
reagan model
during iran contra because it's not the crime
that brings them down
it's the cover-up of the crime
you know look at scooter liby
scooter liby never leaked valerie claims name
to the to robert no back
uh... deputies secretary state rich armadage did
but it was scooter liby who was put on trial and and what would be convicted of
he was convicted
two counts of perjury and three counts of making a false statement
charges that had nothing to do with the leaking of valerie claims name
we're gonna see the same situation now
it's not necessarily about whatever
president trump or or his people may or may not have committed
it's going to be their response
to this investigation
their response to the accusation of the crime
if they're not careful that's what's going to do them in
so as you look at the current picture what are your uh... most significant
concerns john
well
here i am concerned about so much right now
this was my first trip overseas uh...
trump was elected president
and people at least our european allies are absolutely panicked stricken
you know i thought maybe they would say all trump he's a buffoon he's a
reality tv star
they're panic stricken
this is the guy that has his finger on the nuclear button
and because he's so unpredictable
it actually has an effect on their economy
and on their own society
so that's what they're afraid of
they're desperate for
for a steady hand they're desperate for american leadership
and they're not getting it with donald trump
this is going to be bad not just for the united states
but it's going to be bad for every country in the world that considers itself to
be a friend of the united states
well john it's always a pleasure to talk with you thanks for joining me today
and uh... i want to reference uh... your latest book is doing time like a
spy
how the c i a taught me to survive and thrive in prison
and i see online that sky horse is planning to publish
the convenient terrorist abu's a beta
and the weird wonder wonderland of america's secret wars
uh... when when can we expect to see that
that is a book that i wrote with uh... joe hickman a former guantanamo guard and
an author in his own right i know it's good
uh... he's a good man
yeah good guy and it's going to be published on june the twenty seven
okay well i'm looking forward to that
and uh... maybe i'll have you and joe on together cuz uh... he's done a
great job of uh... of
really reporting on
the burn pits that was his most recent book
uh... and the way the military uh... sacrifice the health of many
service members and support personnel
uh... with the reckless uh... destruction of trash and uh... other
materials
at various locations in iraq
including my best friend from high school
who was in charge of the burn pit in uh... in bagdad
and died of uh... of an extraordinarily rare
form of brain cancer five years ago
i'm sorry
and also uh... joe hickman has been and uh... and a great source and he published
his first book
uh... about the death of three prisoners uh... who they claimed committed
suicide at guantanamo
when the evidence is uh... pretty clear that that's not the case
that's right john pages book thanks for joining us will talk again soon
i'm looking forward to it thanks for having me
former cia officer former federal prisoner john carry out
i'd like to hear your comments email peter at peter b collins dot com